One morning, in the year 1957,
ذات صباح ، في العام 1957
the neurosurgeon Wilder Penfield
جراح الاعصاب والتر بينفيلد
saw himself like this,
رأي نفسه هكذا
a weird freak with huge hands,
مخلوق شاذ غريب بايادي ضخمه
huge mouth,
فم ضخم
and a tiny bottom.
وعجيزة صغيره
Actually this creature
في الحقيقه هذا المخلوق
is the result of the Penfield research.
هو نتيجه لأبحاث بينفيلد
He named it homunculus.
وقد سماه قزم
Basically the homunculus is
أساساً القزم هو
the visualization of a human being
تصور لإنسان
where each part of the body is proportional
بحيث يتناسب كل جزء من الجسم
to the surface it takes in the brain.
مع الحيز الذي يشغله من المخ
So, of course, homunculus is definitely not a freak.
وعليه ، بالطبع ، القزم قطعاً ليس شاذ
It's you. It's me.
فهو أنت ، وهو أنا .
It's our invisible reality.
وهو حقيقتنا الغير مرئيه .
This visualization could explain, for example,
يستطيع هذا التصور أن يشرح ، مثلاً،
why newborns, or smokers,
لماذا حديثي الولاده ، أو المدخنين
put, instinctively, their fingers in the mouth.
يضعون بصوره تلقائيه أصابعهم في فمهم .
Unfortunately it doesn't explain why
للأسف لا تشرح لماذا
so many designers remain mainly interested
كثير من المصممين يحصروا جل إهتمامهم
in designing chairs.
في تصميم الكراسي.
So anyway, even if I do not understand science entirely,
علي أي حال ، حتي وإن لم أفهم العلوم تماماً
for my design I essentially refer to it.
فإنني إرجع إليها بصوره أساسيه في تصاميمي
I'm fascinated by its ability to
أنا مسحور بقدرتها علي أن
deeply investigate the human being,
تبحث بعمق في الإنسان
its way of working, its way of feeling.
طريقته في العمل ، طريقته في التفكير
And it really helps me to understand
وتساعدني حقيقه لأفهم
how we see, how we hear,
كيف نري ، كيف نسمع
how we breathe, how our brain can inform or mislead us.
كيف نتنفس، كيف يمكن لعقلنا أن يخبرنا أو يضللنا .
It's a great tool for me
هي أداه عظيمه بالنسبه لي
to understand what could be our real needs.
لتساعدني لأفهم ما قد يكون حوجتنا الحقيقيه.
Marketing people have never been able to do that.
إخصائي التسويق لم يستطيعوا أبداً فعل ذلك
Marketing reduces things. Marketing simplifies.
التسويق يقلل من الأشياء ، التسويق يبسطها.
Marketing creates user groups.
التسويق يخلق مجموعات مستهلكين
And scientists, amidst complexity,
والعلوم ، بين التعقيد،
amidst fluctuation and uniqueness.
بين التقلب ، والتفرد.
What could be our real needs?
ما الذي يمكن أن يكون حوجتنا الأساسيه؟
Maybe the silence.
قد يكون الصمت.
In our daily life we are continuously disturbed by
في حياتنا اليوميه نتعرض للازعاج بواسطه
aggressive sounds.
الاصوات العنيفه
And you know all those kind of sound puts us
ونعلم أن مثل تلك الأصوات تضعنا في
in a kind of stressful state,
حاله من الإجهاد
and prevent us from being quiet and focused.
وتمنعنا من الهدوء والتركيز.
So I wanted to create a kind of
وعليه أردت أن أبتدع نوع من
sound filter,
مصفي الصوت،
able to preserve ourselves from noise pollution.
يقدر أن يعزلنا من التلوث الضوضائي.
But I didn't want it to make it by
لكني لم أرد أن أصنعه بأن
isolating people, without any earmuffs
أعزل الأشخاص ، بدون سدادات الأذن
or those kind of things.
وما شابهها.
Or neither with including complex technology.
ولا بإدخال تكنولوجيا معقده
I just wanted to, using the complexity
أردت فقط، باستخدام التعقيد
and the technology of the brain, of the human brain.
والتكنلوجيا العقليه ، لعقل الإنسان.
So I worked with white noise.
لذا عملت مع الضجه البيضاء
dB is basically --
د. ب هي أساساً
dB is the name of the product,
د. ب هو إسم المنتج ، اساساً
basically a white noise diffuser.
ناشر الضجه البيضاء.
This is white noise.
هذه هي الضجه البيضاء.
The white noise is the sum of all frequencies
الضجه البيضاء هي مجموع جميع الترددات
that are audible by the human being,
المسموعه للإنسان
brought to the same intensity.
الموجهه بنفس الشده
And this noise is like a "shhhhhhhhhhhhh," like that.
وهذه الضجه مثل (ششششششششش) هكذا.
And this noise is the most neutral.
وهذه الضجه هي الأكثر حياداً
It is the perfect sound for our ears and our brain.
هي الصوت المثالي لأذاننا و عقولنا.
So when you hear this sound
فعندما تستمع لهذا الصوت.
you feel like a kind of shelter,
تشعر بنوع من الوقايه
preserved from noise pollution.
محمي من التلوث الضوضائي.
And when you hear the white noise, your brain is immediately focused on it.
وعندما تسمع الضجه البيضاء يركز عقلك فيها فوراً
And do not be disturbed any more by the other aggressive sound.
ولا تنزعج بعد ذلك من الأصوات العنيفه الأخري.
It seems to be magic.
تبدو كالسحر.
But it is just physiology. It's just in your brain.
لكنه فقط علم وظائف الأعضاء. فقط في عقلك .
And in mine, I hope.
وعقلي. كما آمل .
So in order to make this white noise
ولكي نصنع هذه الضجه البيضاء.
a little bit active and reactive,
بصوره نشطه ومتفاعله أكثر.
I create a ball, a rolling ball
إبتدعت كره، كره تتدحرج
able to analyze and find
قابله أن تحلل و تجد
where does aggressive sound come from,
من أين تأتي الأصوات العنيفه ،
and roll, at home or at work,
وتتدحرج ، في المنزل أو العمل ،
towards aggressive noise,
لتقابل الضجه العنيفه ،
and emits white noise in order to neutralize it.
وتبعث ضجه بيضاء في سبيل تحييدها .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It works.
لقد نجحت.
You feel the effect of the white noise?
هل تشعر بأثر الضجه البيضاء؟
It's too in silence.
إنها أيضاً في صمت.
If you make some noise you can feel the effect.
إذا أحدثت بعض الضجه سوف تشعر بأثرها.
So even if this object,
حتي إذا كان هذا الشئ
even if this product includes some technology,
حتي لو إحتوي هذا المنتج علي بعض التكنولوجيا،
it includes some speakers, it includes some microphones
يحتوي علي بعض السماعات ، المكرفونات ،
and some electronic devices,
وبعض الأجهزه الألكترونيه،
this object is not a very smart object.
هذا الشئ ليس ذكياً جداً
And I don't want to make a very smart object.
وأنا لا أرغب في صناعة شئ ذكي جداً
I don't want to create a perfect object like a perfect robot.
لا أود أن أبتدع شئ مثالي كالرجل الآلي المثالي
I want to create an object like you and me.
أود أن أبتدع شئ مثلي ومثلك.
So, definitely not perfect.
بالتأكيد ليس مثالياً
So imagine, for instance, you are at home.
تخيل، مثلاً، أنك في المنزل
A loving dispute with your girl or boyfriend.
حدث نزاع بينك وبين حبيبك أو حبيبتك
You shout. You say, "Blah blah blah, Blah blah blah. Who is this guy?"
وبدأت بالصراخ. تقول " بلا بلا بلا بلا ، من هو هذا الشاب ؟ "
And dB will probably roll toward you.
و د.ب ربما يبدأ بالتدحرج نحوك.
And turning around you is "shhhhhhh," like that.
ووتحوم حولك "ششششششششششششش" هكذا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Definitely not perfect. So you would probably
بالتأكيد ليس مثالياً. وربما قد
shut it, at this point.
تركله بعيداً، في هذه اللحظه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Anyway, in this same kind of approach,
علي أي حال ، علي نفس السياق
I designed K.
قمت بتصميم "ك"
K is a daylight receiver transmitter.
"ك" هو محول لاقط لضوء النهار.
So this object is supposed to be displayed on your desk,
هذا الكائن من المفترض أن تضعه علي مكتبك
or on your piano, where you are supposed
أو علي البيانو، أينما كان مقدراً
to spend most of your time in the day.
أن تمضي معظم وقتك نهاراً.
And this object will be
وهذا الكائن يكون
able to know exactly the quantity of light you receive during the day,
قادراً علي أن يعرف كميه الضوء الذي يصلك خلال النهار.
and able to give you the quantity of light you need.
وقادراً علي أن يمدك بالضوء الذي تحتاجه.
This object is completely covered by
هذا الكائن مغطي تماماً
fiber opticals.
بالألياف البصريه
And the idea of those fiber opticals is to inform the object, for sure,
والفكره في هذه الألياف البصريه هي أن تخبر الكائن بصوره مؤكده
but creates the idea of an
بل أن تمثل
eye sensibility of the object.
حساسيه العين للكائن.
I want, by this design
أود بهذا التصميم ،
feel, when you see it,
عندما تراه،
you see, instinctively,
تري ، بصوره غريزيه،
this object seems to be very sensitive,
هذا الكائن يبدو حساساً جداً،
very reactive.
فعال جداً
And this object knows, better than you
وهذا الكائن يعرف أفضل منك
and probably before you, what you really need.
وربما قبلك ، ما الذي تحتاجه فعلاً.
You have to know that the lack of daylight
يجب أن تعلم أن قلة ضوء النهار
can provoke some
قد يُحدث بعض
problem of energy, or problem of libido.
المشاكل في الطاقه، أو الرغبه الجنسيه
So, a huge problem.
وعليه ، مشاكل ضخمه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Most of the projects I work on --
معظم المشاريع التي أعمل عليها..
I live in collaboration with scientists.
أعيش في معايره مع العلماء
I'm just a designer. So I need them.
أنا مصمم فقط . لذلك أحتاجهم.
So there can be some biologists,
لذا من الممكن أن يكونو بعض علماء الأحياء
psychiatrists, mathematicians, and so on.
علماء النفس، علماء الرياضيات ، وهكذا.
And I submit them, my intuitions,
وأسلمهم حدسي،
my hypothesis, my first ideas.
فرضياتي، افكاري الأوليه.
And they react. They told me what is possible, what is impossible.
ومن ثم يردون ، يخبرونني ما هو الممكن وما المستحيل.
And together we improve the original concept.
وسوياً نطور المفهوم الأصلي
And we build the project to the end.
ونبني المشروع حتي النهاية.
And this kind of relationship between designer and scientist
وهذا النوع من العلاقه بين المصمم والعالم
started when I was at school.
بدأ منذ كنت في المدرسه.
Indeed in my studies I was a guinea pig
قديماً في سنوات دراستي كنت متخصص في الخنزير بحر هندي
for a pharmaceutical industry.
لصناعة الصيدله.
And the irony for me was
وكانت المفارقه بالنسبه لي
of course, I didn't do that for the sake of science progress.
بالطبع لم أكن أفعل ذلك من أجل الأرتقاء بالعلوم
I just do that to make money.
كنت أفعل ذلك فقط لكسب المال.
Anyway, this project, or this experience,
علي أي حال ، هذا المشروع ، أو هذه التجربه،
make me start a new project on the design of medicine.
جعلتني أبدا مشروع جديد في تصميم الأدويه.
You have to know that today, roughly one or two every drug pills
يجب أن تعوا اليوم أن ، تقريباً واحده أو أثنتين من حبوب الدواء
is not taken correctly.
لا تؤخذ بشكل صحيح.
So even if the active constituents
عليه حتي إذا كان المكون الفعال
in pharmaceuticals made constant progress
وتقوم المكونات بتقدم ثابت
in terms of chemistry, target of stability,
من حيث الكيمياء، والهدف، والإستقرار،
the behavior of the patients
فإن سلوك المريض
goes more and more unstable.
يزيد في عدم الإستقرار
So we took too many of them.
لذا أخذنا العديد منهم
We took irregular dosage.
أخذنا جرعات غير منتظمه
We do not follow instructions. And so on.
لا تتبع لتعليمات . وما إلي ذلك.
So I wanted to create a
وأردت أن أنتج
new kind of medicine,
نوع جديد من الأدويه
in order to create a new kind of relationship
حتي أبتدع نوع جديد من العلاقات
between the patient and the treatment.
بين المريض والعلاج.
So I turned traditional pills into this.
لذا غيرت الحبوب العاديه إلي هذا.
I'm going to give you some example.
ساقوم بإعطائكم مثال.
This one is an antibiotic.
هذا هو مضاد حيوي
And its purpose is to help patient
والقصد منه هو أن يساعد المريض
to go to the end of the treatment.
حتي نهايه العلاج.
And the concept is to
والمفهوم هو أن
create a kind of onion,
أنتج نوع من البصل
a kind of structure in layers.
يحتوي علي طبقات
So, you start with the darkest one.
إذن، تبدأ بذات اللون الأكثر قتامه
And you are helped to visualize the duration of the treatment.
وتساعدك علي أن تتصور مراحل العلاج.
And you are helped to visualize the decrease of the infection.
وتتصور تلاشي العدوي تدريجياً
So the first day, this is the big one.
إذن في اليوم الأول ، هذه الكبيره الحجم.
And you have to peel and eat one layer a day.
وعليك أن تقشر وتأكل طبقة واحده في اليوم.
And your antibiotic goes smaller and clearer.
و يصبح المضاد الحيوي أصغر حجماً وأكثر وضوحاً.
And you're waiting for recovery as you were waiting for the Christmas day.
وتنتظر الشفاء كما تنتظر يوم عيد الميلاد.
And you follow the treatment like that,
وهكذا تتبع العلاج
to the end of the treatment.
حتي نهايه العلاج.
And here you can get the white core.
وعندها يمكنك الحصول علي النواه البيضاء.
And it means, right, you are in the recovery.
وتعني أن هذا حقيقي، لقد شُفيت.
(Applause) Thank you.
(تصفيق) أشكركم . ( تصفيق)
This one is a "third lung,"
هذه تُدعي ( الرئه الثالثه)
a pharmaceutical device for long-term asthma treatment.
جهاز صيدلاني لعلاج الأزمه علي المدي البعيد.
I designed it to help kids to follow the treatment.
صممته لأساعد الأطفال لإتباع العلاج.
So the idea of this one is to create
فالفكره وراء هذا الجهاز أن نبتدع
a relationship between the patient of the treatment
علاقه بين المريض والعلاج.
but a relationship of dependency.
لكنها علاقه تبعيه.
But in this case it is not the medication that is dependent on the patient.
لكن في هذه الحاله ليس المريض هو الذي يعتمد علي العلاج
This is, the kids will feel
فالطفل سوف يشعر
the therapeutic object needs him.
بأن الكائن العلاجي يحتاج إليه
So the idea is, all night long
إذن الفكره هي، طوال الليل
the elastic skin of the third lung
الجلد المرن للرئه الثالثه
will slowly inflate itself,
يفتح نفسه ببطء
including air and molecules, for sure.
بما في ذلك الهواء والجزئيات، بالتأكيد.
And when the kids wake up,
وعندما يستيقظ الطفل
he can see the object needs him. And he take him to his mouth,
سوف يري أن الكائن العلاجي يحتاجه. فيأخذه نحو فمه،
and breathe the air it contains.
ويستنشق منه الهواء.
So by this way,
وبهذه الطريقه،
the kid, to take care of himself,
ليهتم الطفل بنفسه،
is to take care of this living object.
سوف يهتم بهذا الكائن الحي.
And he does not feel anymore it's relies on asthma treatment,
ولا يشعر إطلاقاً بأنه يعتمد علي علاج الأزمه.
as the asthma treatment needs him.
لأن علاج الأزمه يعتمد عليه.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
In this guise of living object approach,
في هذا النوع من منهج الكائن الحي
I like the idea of a kind of invisible design,
أحب فكره التصميم الغير مرئي
as if the function of the object
وكأن دور الكائن
exists in a kind of invisible field
موجود في نوع من المجال الغير مرئي
just around the objects themselves.
فقط حول الكائنات نفسها.
We could talk about a kind of soul,
يمكن أن نتحدث حول نوع من الحس
of a ghost accompanying them.
لشبح مسخر لهم.
And almost a kind of poltergeist effect.
وتقريباً نوع من تأثير الأرواح.
So when a passive object like this one seems to be alive,
فعندما تدب الحياه في كائن ساكن كهذا.
because it is -- woosh -- starting to move.
لأنه بدا بالحركه.
And I remember an exhibition design
وأتذكر ، تصميم لمعرض،
I made for John Maeda,
صممته لجون ميدا،
and for the Fondation Cartier in Paris.
ولمؤسسه كارتييه في باريس.
And John Maeda was supposed to show
و جون ميدا كان من المفترض أن يقدم
several graphic animations in this exhibition.
عدة رسوم متحركه في هذا المعرض.
And my idea for this exhibition design was to create
وفكرتي لهذا المعرض التصميمي كانت أن أبتدع
a real pong game, like this one.
لعبه كره طاوله حقيقيه، كهذه.
And the idea was to create some self-moving benches
والفكره أن ابتدع بعض المقاعد ذاتيه الحركه
in the main exhibition room.
في غرفه العرض الرئيسيه.
So the living benches would be exactly like the ball.
إذن المقاعد الحيه ستكون بالضبط كالكره.
And John was so excited by this idea. He said to me, "Okay let's go."
وكان جون متحمساً جداً لهذه الفكره، وقال لي :" حسناً لنبدأ"
I remember the day of the opening.
أتذكر جيداً يوم الإفتتاح.
I was a little bit late.
وصلت متأخراً قليلاً.
When I bring the 10 living and self-moving benches
عندما أحضرت المقاعد العشره ذاتيه الحركه
in the exhibition room, John was just beside me,
إلي غرفه العرض، كان جون بجانبي،
and was like, "Hmm. Hmm."
وكان يهمهم.
And he told me, after a long silence,
وقال لي ، بعد صمت طويل،
"I wonder, Mathieu, if
"أتساءل ماثيو ، إذا
people won't be more fascinated by your benches
كان الحضور سيندهشوا بمقاعدك أكثر
than by my videos."
من أفلامي."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It would be a great honor, a great compliment for me,
سوف يكون شرف عظيم ، و إطراء عظيم لي .
if he hadn't decided to take all them off
إذا لم أقرر أن أبعدهم جميعاً
two hours before the opening.
قبل ساعتين من الإفتتاح.
So, huge tragedy.
إذن، مأساه ضخمه.
I guess you won't be surprised if I tell you
لا أعتقد أنكم ستستغربون إذا أخبرتكم
that Pinocchio is one of my great influences.
بأن لبنيوكيو عظيم الأثر عليّ.
Pinocchio is probably one of my best design products, my favorite one.
بنوكيو قد يكون هو أفضل تصميماتي المنتجه
Because it is a kind of object with a conscience,
لأنه من نوع الكائنات التي لها ضمير
able to be modified by its surroundings,
قابل للتعديل تبعاً للمحيط.
and able to modify it as well.
وقابل لتعديله أيضاً.
The other great influence is the mine's canary.
المؤثر الكبير الأخر هو كناري المنجم.
In coal mines, this canary
في مناجم الفحم، هذه الكناري
was supposed to be close to the miners.
من المفترض أن تكون قريبه من عمال المناجم.
And it was singing all day long. And when it stops it means that it just died.
وهي تغني طوال اليوم. وعندما تتوقف يعني أنها قد ماتت.
So this canary was a living alarm,
إذن هذه الكناري هي منبه حي.
and a very efficient one.
ومنبه دقيق جداً.
A very natural technology,
ذو تقنيه طبيعيه جداً،
in order to say to the miners,
حتي تقول لعمال المناجم،
"The air is too bad. You have to go. It's an emergency."
"الهواء سئ جداً. يجب أن تذهبوا. إنها حاله طارئه."
So it's, for me, a great product.
إذن بالنسبه لي، هي منتج عظيم.
And I tried to design a kind of canary.
حاولت أن أصمم هذا النوع من الكناري.
Andrea is one.
أندريا واحده منهم.
Andrea is a living air filter that absorbs toxic gasses
أندريا هي مصفي هواء حي يمتص الغازات السامه
from air, contaminated indoor air.
من الهواء، الهواء الداخلي الملوث .
So it uses some plants to do this job,
وتستخدم بعض النباتات لتقوم بهذه المهمه،
selected for their gas-filtering ability.
منتقاه لقدرتها العاليه لتصفيه الغاز.
You have to know, or you probably already know,
يجب أن تعرف، وربما تعرف بالفعل
that indoor air pollution is more toxic than outdoor one.
تلوث الهواء الداخلي أخطر من التلوث الخارجي.
So while I'm talking to you,
إذن بينما أتحدث إليكم الأن،
the seats you are sitting on are currently emitting some
المقعد الذي تجلسون عليه يبعث بعض
invisible and odorless toxic gas. Sorry for that. (Laughter)
الغازات السامه عديمه اللون والرائحه. أعتذر لهذا.
So you are currently breathing formaldehyde.
إذن حالياً تستنشقون الفورمهايدليد.
It's the same for me with the carpet.
والشئ نفسه يحدث لي مع السجاد.
And this is exactly the same at home.
وبالضبط يحدث نفس الشئ في المنزل.
Because all the product we get constantly give away
لأن معظم المنتجات التي نقتنيها تطرح بإستمرار
the volatile component of which they're made of.
المكونات المتطائره التي صُنعت منها.
So let's have a look at your home.
إذن دعونا نلقي نظره علي منازلكم.
So your sofa, your plastic chair,
أريكتكم ، مقعدكم البلاستيكي،
your kid's toys
ألعاب أطفالكم
give their own invisible reality. And this one is very toxic.
لديهم حقيقتهم الغير مرئيه. وهذا سام جداً.
This is the reason why
وهذا هو السبب لماذا
I created, with David Edward,
إخترعت مع ديفيد إدوارد،
a scientist of Harvard University,
العالم من جامعه هارفرد،
an object able to absorb the toxic elements using those kind of plants.
كائن يمكنه إمتصاص العناصر السامه بإستخدام تلك الأنواع من النباتات.
But the idea is to force
لكن الفكره هي أن تُجبر
the air to go in the effective part of the plants.
الهواء أن يدخل إلي الجزء الفاعل من النبات.
Because the roots of the plant are not very effective.
لأن جذور النبات ليست فعاله جداً
Bill Wolverton from NASA
بيل ويلفرتون من ناسا
analyzed it cleverly in the '70s.
حلله بذكاء في السبعينات
So the idea is to create an object
إذن الفكره هي إختراع كائن
able to force the air, and to be in contact at the right speed
يقدر علي أن يجبر الهواء ويكون علي إتصال بالسرعه الصحيحه
at the right place, in all the effective parts of the plant.
والمكان الصحيح، في الجزء الصحيح من النبات.
So this is the final object.
إذن هذا هو الكائن الأخير.
It will be launched next September.
سوف نطلقه في سبتمبر القادم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This one is kind of the same approach
هذا النوع من التوجه
because I include, in a product
لأنني قد ضمّنت في المنتج
like Andrea, some plants.
مثل أندريا، بعض النباتات.
And in this one, plants are used for the water filtration ability.
ويستخدم هذا النبات لقدرته علي تصفيه المياه.
And it includes some fishes as well.
ويحتوي علي بعض الأسماك أيضاً.
But here, unlike Andrea,
لكن هنا، بخلاف أندريا
here are supposed to be eaten.
من المفترض أن يؤكل.
Indeed, this object is a domestic farm,
بالتأكيد، هذا الكائن عباره عن مزرعه محليه،
for fishes and green.
للأسماك والنباتات.
So the idea of this object
إذن الفكره لهذا الكائن
is to be able to get at home
أن يكون في مقدوره أن يحصل في المنزل
very local food.
علي طعام محلي.
The locavores
(اللوكوفريين- مستهلكي الطعام المحلي)
used to get food
إعتادوا علي أن يحصلوا علي الطعام
taken in a radius of 100 miles.
من داخل المئه ميل المحيطه بهم
Local River is able to provide you
النهر المحلي يستطيع أن يقدم لك
food directly in your living room.
الطعام مباشره من غرفه معيشتك.
So the principle of this object
إذن جوهر هذا الشئ
is to create an ecosystem
هو أن نبتدع نظام بيئي
called aquaponics.
نسميه النظام الغذائي المائي
And the aquaponics is the dirty water of the fish,
والنظام الغذائي المائي هو المياه المتسخه للأسماك
by a water pump, feeds the plants above.
تغذي النباتات بواسطه مضخه مياه
And the plants will filter, by the roots,
والنباتات سوف تنقي بواسطه جذورها
the dirty water of the fish.
مياه الأسماك المتسخه
After, it goes back into the fish tank.
لتعود بعدها إلي حوض الأسماك
After that you have two options.
بعد ذلك لديك خيارين
Or you sit down in front of it like you would do in front your TV set.
أن تجلس أمامها كما تفعل أمام التلفاز
Amazing channel.
قناة رائعه
Or you start fishing.
أو أن تبدأ بالصيد
And you make some sushis with a fish
وأن تصنع بعض السوشي بالأسماك
and the aromatic plants above.
وبعض النباتات العطريه.
Because you can grow some potatoes.
لأنك يمكن أن تزرع بعض البطاطس.
No, not potatoes, but tomatoes,
لا ، ليس بطاطس، ولكن طماطم،
aromatic plants and so on.
نباتات عطريه وما إلي ذلك.
So now we can breathe safely.
الآن يمكنك ان تتنفس بأمان.
Now we can eat local food.
الآن يمكنك أن تأكل طعام محلي.
Now we can be treated by smart medicine.
الان يمكن أن نُعالج بالدواء الذكي.
Now we can be well-balanced in our biorhythm
الأن يمككنا أن نكون متوازنين جيداً في نظامنا البيولوجي
with daylight.
مع ضوء النهار.
But it was important to create a perfect place,
لكن من المهم أن نبتدع مكان مثالي،
so I tried to,
لذلك حاولت أن،
in order to work and create.
من أجل أن أعمل وأخترع
So I designed, for an American scientist based in Paris,
لذا صممت، لعالم أمريكي مستقر في باريس،
a very stimulative, brain-stimulative office.
شئ محفز جداً، مكتب محفز للدماغ ،
I wanted to create a perfect place
أردت أن أخترع المكان المثالي
where you can work and play,
حيث تستطيع أن تعمل و تلعب،
and where your body and your brain can work together.
حيث يستطيع جسدك وعقلك العمل معاً.
So, in this office,
إذن، في هذا المكتب،
you do not work anymore at your desk, like a politician.
لم تعد تعمل في مكتبك ، مثل السياسيين.
Your seat, your sleep and your play
مقعدك، مكان نومك و لعبك
on a big geodesic island made of leather.
في جزيره مصنوعه من الجلد.
See, like this one?
أنظر، مثل هذه؟
In this office you do not work and write and draw on a sheet of paper,
في هذا المكتب أنت لا تعمل و تكتب و ترسم في ورقه،
but you draw directly on a kind of huge whiteboard cave,
بل ترسم مباشره في سبوره بيضاء ضخمه علي شكل كهف
like a prehistoric scientist.
مثل عالم من عصر ما قبل التاريخ
So you, like that, can make some sport during your work.
إذن أنت هكذا تلعب الرياضه أثناء العمل.
In this office
في هذا المكتب
you do not need to go out
لا تحتاج إلي الخروج
in order to be in contact with nature.
لتتواصل مع الطبيعه
You include, directly, the nature in the floor of the office.
تُضمن الطبيعه مباشره في أرضيه المكتب
You can see it there.
يمكنك أن تراها هنا.
This is an inspiration image
هذه الصوره ملهمه
to lead this project of the office.
لتقود لمشروع المكتب هذا
It really helped me to design it.
لقد ساعدتني حقاً في أن أصممه.
I never show it to my client. He would be so afraid.
لم اُرها لزبوني ابداً. كان ليشعر بالإهانه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Just for my workshop.
فقط لمعملي
I guess it may be the revenge of the guinea pig I was.
اعتقد أنها قد تكون إنتقاماً لخنزير بحر هندي الذي كنته
But it's maybe the conviction
لكن يمكنها أن تكون قناعتنا
as monkey and homunculus we are.
نحن كقرود و أقزام .
All of us need to be considered according to our real nature.
جميعنا يجب أن نُقدر وفقاً لطبيعتنا الحقيقيه.
Thank you very much.
أشكركم جزيل الشكر
(Applause)
(تصفيق)